Guide to the Traugott Lawler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Traugott Lawler papers
1931-2012
MS 2023
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.0
(24 boxes)
This collection consists of material related to a two volume set of Jankyn's Book of Wikked Wyves, edited by Ralph Hanna III and Traugott Lawler as part of the Modern Language Association's Chaucer Library Series. In the first volume, Hanna and Lawler presented comprehensive versions of the three medieval texts that comprised Jankyn's "Book of Wikked Wives" which is referenced in "The Wife of Bath's Tale" in The Canterbury Tales. In the second volume, Hanna and Lawler presented the known contemporary commentaries on one of the three texts, Walter Map's "Dissuasio Valerii," or "The Letter of Valerius to His Friend Ruffinus, Dissuading Him from Marrying." The bulk of the material consists of transcriptions, translations, glosses and reproductions of portions of the commentaries, which were used during the production of volume two. It includes some material not in the published work. The collection also includes drafts of volume one and correspondence related to the project.
Lawler, Traugott, 1937-
Chaucer, Geoffrey, -1400 ( Canterbury tales, Wife of Bath's tale)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Traugott Lawler, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
Traugott Lawler received his B.A. from College of the Holy Cross in 1958, an M.A. from University of Wisconsin in 1962, and a Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1966. He was a member of the Yale faculty from 1966 to 1972, taught at Northwestern University from 1972 to 1982, and returned to Yale in 1981.
In 1981, Lawlor and Ralph Hanna were asked to take over a project on the sources of the "Book of Wikked Wyves" mentioned by the Wife of Bath in the Canterbury Tales. Originally begun by Yale Professor Karl Young (1879-1943) in the 1930s, the work was continued by his student, Robert Armstrong Pratt (1907-1987). The notes, microfilm and other research materials collected by Young and Pratt were divided between Hanna and Lawler and served as the basis for the two volume set of Jankyn's Book of Wikked Wyves,, with volume one, The Primary Texts, published in 1997 and volume 2, Seven Commentaries on Walter Map's "Dissuasio Valerii", published in 2014.
A medievalist scholar and an expert on William Langland, his other published works include The One and the Many in the Canterbury Tales and The Parisiana Poetria of John of Garland, as well as numerous journal articles. After his retirement from Yale in 2005, Lawlor continued his academic work as emeritus professor of English.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material related to a two volume set of Jankyn's Book of Wikked Wyves, edited by Ralph Hanna III and Traugott Lawler as part of the Modern Language Association's Chaucer Library Series. In the first volume, Hanna and Lawler presented comprehensive versions of the three medieval texts that comprised Jankyn's "Book of Wikked Wives" which is referenced in "The Wife of Bath's Tale" in The Canterbury Tales. In the second volume, Hanna and Lawler presented the known contemporary commentaries on one of the three texts, Walter Map's "Dissuasio Valerii," or "The Letter of Valerius to His Friend Ruffinus, Dissuading Him from Marrying." The bulk of the material consists of transcriptions, translations, glosses and reproductions of portions of the commentaries, which were used during the production of volume two. It includes some material not in the published work. The collection also includes drafts of volume one and correspondence related to the project.
Arrangement
The material is arranged as received from the creator of the records.
Lawler, Traugott, 1937-; Hanna, Ralph
- General project records, 1947-2012, undated
  Scope and Contents
  This material includes correspondence, draft of introduction, glosses, notes, texts, and translations.
  - Lewis comments on a late draft, Circa 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Prospectus, Book of Wicked Wives (BWW), 1983-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book of Wicked Wives, general, 1981-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1947-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General
    Letter, dated 5 March 1984, to George B. Young, briefly describes the actions taken and plans for the continuation of the "Book of Wikked Wyves" project begun by Karl Young which Lawler and Ralph Hanna had taken over from Robert Pratt in 1981.
  - Hanna correspondence, 1980-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Volume one introduction, Circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dissuasio text, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Valerius notes, RH, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jerome, Circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Wicked wifes" manuscripts, etc., Circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wicked wives - Jerome editions, Circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Theophrastus, Circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Harley 3724 (Lucinia), Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Grues text and translation, 1988-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ridewall translation, 2008-2012, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Trivet notes, 1989-1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Religiosos, 1963-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Parvus, 1984-2005, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Short commentary, Univ Coll 61," Valerius qui dictur parvus", 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - University 61, Trivet, 1950-1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Erfurt Amplonium Folio 71, 1947-1950, ondated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Oxford, University College, Ms 61, Film 17b, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lincoln 81 (Lo) (Trivet), Circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lambeth 330, 1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Eneas and Paul, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Eneas-Paul Mss collation, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Berlin 540, 1985-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Glosses (my pages, includes Berlin 54), Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minor glossed mss, 1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Microfilm requests, 1976-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Lists of manuscripts on microfilm, 1931-1948, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Drafts of volume one, with additional material, 1983-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Ridewall transcription, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Trivet transcription, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
- Robert Pratt's transcription of the version of Trivet in Ms University 61 ("U"), 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- Robert Pratt's transcription of Ms Lambeth 330, Undated (Box 6, Folder 3-6)
- Ralph Hanna's transcription and translation of Ms Lambeth 330, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
- Microfilm and copies list by commentary, Circa 2012 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Copies of commentaries
  - General manuscript photocopies, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3-6)
  - Grues
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Grues and Ridewall combined
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7-8, Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 10)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 24)
  - Ridewall
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9-16)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 11–14)
  - Trivet
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 17-21, Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 15–17)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 24)
  - Trivet and Religiosos
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 7, Folder 22-23)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 18–19)
  - Trivet and Parvus
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 20–22)
  - Eneas
    - Copyflow and photocopies, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2-16)
    - Microfilm, Undated (Reel 23)